DAN KLEIN: So, we know that if we want
to do well, we have to use depth
limited search in order to
make this practical.
We have to plug in a good evaluation
function but still, because minimax is
so good at these kinds of tactical
decisions, we'd like to go as deeply
into the tree as possible.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to look for ways to prune the
tree to look for branches that
do not have to be analyzed.
So let's go back to the minimax example
where the tree is slowly
revealed to us.
Right.
In this example, we went to the first
child and we saw by examining its
children that it's minimax
value is three.
So we know here that this minimax
value here is three.
Now, let's think about
what happened here.
This node ended up being a two.
When we saw that first child, we
didn't yet know what its min
was going to be.
Right?
Its min could be two.
It could be negative 10.
It could be negative a million.
But we know it's two or lower.
Now we kept doing the computation to
see that yes, indeed, it's two.
But we knew from that very first
child it was already going
to be two or lower.
Over here, we didn't actually know
until the end that it was
also going to be two.
So let's think about whether
or not we could have
accomplished any pruning there.
Well, for the first child, you got to
look at all the children to see that
this is a three.
Right?
What I mean by you have to look at all
the children, is that eight could have
been a negative 10 and we don't know
what to return unless we see it.
When we get to the second child,
the situation's very different.
So as soon as we see this two,
what are we going to return?
Well, I don't know what we're going to
return, but it's going to be less than
or equal to two.
And what's the guy up top doing?
The guy up top's picking the maximum
of these, which means two, one,
negative a billion, it's all equally
going to be unchosen.
Right?
Two or lower?
Why are we even wasting time figuring
out just exactly how cataclysmically
bad this is for MAX?
MAX is already not going to choose it.
So we can just keep going.
As long as we know that the number we
returned isn't necessarily the minimax
value, it's just a value that we know is
good enough to let the rest of the
computation go through.
So we get to this last child.
Let's see if we can save any work.
Well, here's a 14.
What do we know?
We know less than or equal to 14.
Well, if it's 14, MAX
is going to pick it.
So we got to keep going.
Right?
What's five?
That means we scratch that out and
we say less than or equal to 5.
Well MAX is still going to pick it.
So we can't stop.
Because it could be five.
It could be the best thing for MAX.
Or it could still be negative a million
and MAX won't touch it.
So we have to actually look at that
last child and now we see that, in
fact, it's a two.
And we can continue on at the
root and return three.
So sometimes we can prune
and sometimes we can't.
And the key idea is you can
prune after that two--
right here, you can prune this stuff,
because you know this node, which is a
candidate for MAX, you know it's already
worse than another candidate.
You know it's worse then this three.
So as soon as one of these nodes that's
minimizing drops below three,
we can just stop.
That's the key idea about minimax
pruning, and will give us the
algorithm of alpha-beta planning.
Here's the general case for
alpha-beta pruning.
Let's think about what computation we
do in this minimax style search.
Well, let's think about the case where
we're computing the MIN value at some
note N. So that's this
node right here.
What do we do when we compute
the minimum value?
Well, we loop over N's children.
As we loop over the children, what
happens to this running MIN?
We saw this earlier.
That MIN start at positive infinity
and it slowly ticks down as I see
smaller and smaller children.
So we've got some estimate of the MIN.
It's an estimate.
And it's dropping, dropping,
dropping, dropping.
So that's what happens in MIN value.
You have an estimate and it drops.
Well, who cares about the
value of this node?
Well, this node.
MAX cares about it.
So we're computing some value for N,
that MAX is going to use to decide
whether or not this is going to
be a choice that's going to
be the minimax choice.
So let's imagine that somewhere higher
in the tree, MAX can achieve A. So
here's a place where MAX, by choosing
this action here, can force a value of
A. In particular, let's let
A be the best such thing.
So A is the best choice for MAX anywhere
along the path to the root.
So now here we're computing N.
We know the MAX can choose A
somewhere else in the tree.
As soon as N becomes worse than
A, MAX will not choose it.
Now the reason MAX doesn't choose it
may be that we choose another child
here, or another child here,
or another child all the
way up where A was.
So we don't know exactly where N is
going to be out of the running.
But we know that since MAX can force
at least a value of A right here,
there is no chance that N is going to
be the value the propagates up.
In essence, if N becomes worse than A
because MAX will avoid it, we can stop
considering the other children and we
can just cut off the search there.
There's a symmetric version to MAX where
we keep track of B, which is
going to be the best choice higher
in the tree for MIN and we do the
symmetric computation.
But I think the MIN version
is easier to think about.
How do we build this thing?
Well it's called alpha-beta pruning.
You always keep track of
two important numbers.
Alpha is the best option for MAX.
Not anywhere in the tree that we've ever
seen in depth research, is the
best option on the way to the root.
So it's kind of still active
on this game path.
So alpha is the best option for
MAX on the way to the root.
Beta is the best option for MIN
on the way to the root.
And so we still have this MAX and
MIN value computation and
they look the same.
Let's look at the MAX version.
They initialize some counter.
They go through the children improving
that bound, except now they have a
short circuit that says for MAX, if this
thing ever gets so large that MIN
prefers beta elsewhere in
the tree, just stop.
In addition to having a short circuit
that compares against beta, we also
need to keep track of the fact that
alpha is actually increasing as we see
these children, or at least it's
increasing for things lower in the
tree when we recurse.
So alpha-beta's a pretty
cool algorithm.
Doing all of this running-- and it can
be a lot of pruning, you'll see in
your projects--
it has no effect on the minimax value
you compute for the root.
So you're ignoring branches
all over the place.
You're cutting things off left and
right, mostly right, actually.
You'll see why.
You're cutting off all of these branches
and yet you still return the
same value at the root.
However, as we saw, the values
of nodes other than the
root may not be correct.
Remember we returned a value that
said two, maybe smaller?
We don't actually know the
value in those cases.
So although the value at the root would
be correct, the value of other
nodes may be wrong.
Who cares?
This is why we care.
Let's look at this little tree.
If we run minimax, we'll compute the
whole tree, which is really big.
Right?
Look, three nodes.
OK.
So what we do in alpha-beta is we say,
all right, here you're a 10.
When I recurse into the right child, I'm
going to look at the first child
and say, OK, that's a 10.
According to the rule, we can actually
end right now, return 10, cut off this
branch, and we'll be sure that the
number at the root is not changed from
if we had actually done the full minimax
computation, which would have
had a zero on the right but it still
would have had a ten at the root.
So cutting off that zero didn't change
the value of the root, but if what I
wanted was not the minimax value of the
root, which is rarely what you're
after, but rather to know
the optimal action.
Well, there's only one optimal
action and it's to go left.
Whereas under alpha-beta, actually
they look the same.
So you can't just apply this naively
for action selection.
There are various ways
you can modify it.
You reinforce inequality in the check
you can run each child separately.
There are fancier ways to string
them together, but you'll have
to be aware of this.
This is one of the complexities
of your project.
It's not enough to be
right at the root.
You have to be right at the children of
the root because they're the ones
you're going to use to
pick your action.
If you build alpha-beta pruning and
you do a pretty good job of trying
that good children before the bad
children, you can get much more
effective at going deeper into the tree
because you're basically reducing
the branching factor.
With perfect ordering, effectively,
you take the square root of the
branching factor, which means you
double the depth that you're
able to search to.
Now, of course, you're still not going
to go to a full depth of something
like chess, but going twice as deep
is a big deal for these games.
This algorithm is also cool because it's
a simple example of what's called
metareasoning or metacomputation, which
is doing computation to figure
out what computation you should do.
Here we're keeping track of all these
alphas and betas so that we can decide
whether or not to recurse
and that's awesome.